<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:lang ="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

<!-- Information about TEI section -->
     <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Frankenstein</title>
                <author>
                  <persName>Mary Wollstonecraft (Godwin) Shelley</persName>
                </author>

                <editor>
                  <persName>Zijun Ye</persName>
                  <persName>Aditya Kandel</persName>
                </editor>
    
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Henry Colburn and Richard Bentley</publisher>
                <date when="1831">1831</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Frankenstein</title>
                    <author>Mary Wollstonecraft (Godwin) Shelley</author>
                    <publisher>Henry Colburn and Richard Bentley</publisher>
                    <date when="1831">1831</date>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
    <!-- Main body of the transcribed text -->
    <body>
      <div type="chapter" n="16">
        <head>Chapter 16</head>
        <!-- Chapter 16 Material -->
        <p>Cursed, cursed creator! Why did I live? Why, in that instant, did I not extinguish the spark of existence which you had so wantonly bestowed? I know not; despair had not yet taken possession of me; my feelings were those of rage and revenge...</p>
        <!-- Annotation -->
        <note type="analysis">
          This opening demonstrates the Creature's intense existential despair and rage against Victor Frankenstein, highlighting the central theme of creator and creation.
          <bibl>Mary Shelley, Frankenstein, 1818.</bibl>
        </note>

        <p>When night came I quitted my retreat and wandered in the wood; and now, no longer restrained by the fear of discovery, I gave vent to my anguish in fearful howlings...</p>
        <!-- Annotation -->
        <note type="analysis">
          Shelley's use of natural imagery (the "cold stars" and "bare trees") contrasts the Creature's inner turmoil, reinforcing the Romantic preoccupation with nature's indifference.
          <bibl>Critical Source: Mellor, Anne K. "Mary Shelley: Her Life, Her Fiction, Her Monsters," 1988.</bibl>
        </note>

        <p>The sun rose; I heard the voices of men and knew that it was impossible to return to my retreat during that day...</p>
        <!-- Annotation -->
        <note type="analysis">
          The Creature's reflection on his "imprudence" emphasizes his capacity for moral reasoning, challenging assumptions about his monstrosity.
          <bibl>Secondary Source: Cantor, Paul A. "Frankenstein as Modern Myth," 1976.</bibl>
        </note>

        <p>The pleasant sunshine and the pure air of day restored me to some degree of tranquillity; and when I considered what had passed at the cottage...</p>

        <p>As night advanced, I placed a variety of combustibles around the cottage...</p>
        <!-- Annotation -->
        <note type="analysis">
          The act of burning the cottage symbolizes the Creature's descent into vengeance and mirrors Victor's destructive obsession with knowledge.
          <bibl>Mary Shelley, Frankenstein, 1818.</bibl>
        </note>

        <p>And now, with the world before me, whither should I bend my steps? I resolved to fly far from the scene of my misfortunes...</p>

        <p>At this time a slight sleep relieved me from the pain of reflection, which was disturbed by the approach of a beautiful child...</p>
        <!-- Annotation -->
        <note type="analysis">
          The encounter with the child demonstrates the Creature's conflicting desire for connection and capacity for violence when rejected.
          <bibl>Critical Analysis: Baldick, Chris. "In Frankenstein's Shadow," 1987.</bibl>
        </note>

        <p>"Boy, you will never see your father again; you must come with me."</p>
        <p>The child still struggled and loaded me with epithets which carried despair to my heart...</p>

        <p>"This was then the reward of my benevolence! I had saved a human being from destruction, and as a recompense I now writhed under the miserable pain of a wound...</p>
        <!-- Annotation -->
        <note type="analysis">
          The Creature's wound becomes symbolic of the emotional and physical suffering inflicted by humanity's rejection.
          <bibl>Mary Shelley, Frankenstein, 1818.</bibl>
        </note>

        <p>"After some weeks my wound healed, and I continued my journey. The labours I endured were no longer to be alleviated by the bright sun or gentle breezes of spring...</p>

        <p>But my toils now drew near a close, and in two months from this time I reached the environs of Geneva...</p>
        <!-- Annotation -->
        <note type="analysis">
          Geneva, Victor's birthplace, serves as a geographical marker for the Creature's growing identification of Victor as the source of his misery.
          <bibl>Historical Context: Wolfson, Susan J. "Borderlines: The Shiftings of Gender in British Romanticism," 2006.</bibl>
        </note>
      </div>

      <!-- Chapter 17 Material -->
      <div type="chapter" n="17">
        <head>Chapter 17</head>
      </div> 


    </body>
  </text>

</TEI>
